Finding Aid for Bright Sheng Papers, 1962-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Silk Road Trip 2000
  - Silk Road Slides, summer 2000
    - ca. July 14-30, 2000 Qinghai Puppetry Music, [9.16-9.19] (Box 21)
    - One of the local Shaanxi Museums, [9.20] (Box 21)
    - July 30-August 2, 2000 The scenery of Gansu Province I (Mogao Caves), [10.a-t,] (Box 21)
    - July 30-August 2, 2000 The scenery of Gansu Province II, [11.a-t]
      - Jia Yu Gate, a part of great Wall, [11.a-o] (Box 21)
      - Bright Sheng at the Jia Yu Gate, [11.n] (Box 21)
    - July 30-August 2, 2000 Xanxiao singing, People's Square, Wuwei, Gansu Province, [12.a-g] (Box 21)
      (Wuwei is a modern city that used to be called Liang Zhou. Some old blind people singing ballads (story-telling music) in a public park).
    - ca. August 3-4 2000 Pictures in Dun Huang Caves, which cover over fifteen hundred years in history, from ca. 400-1900 AC [AD], [12.k-n] (Box 21)
    - The introduction of the Silk Road at the Silk Road Museum in the Gobi desert, [12.p] (Box 21)
    - The roads of the Silk Road displayed at the Silk Road Museum in the Gobi desert, [12.q] (Box 21)
    - The map of the Silk Road displayed at the Silk Road Museum in the Gobi desert, [12.r] (Box 21)
    - ca. September 1-4 2000 Old fishing boats, Shandong Province, [12.s-t] (Box 21)
    - August 10, 2000 Urumqi, Xinjiang Province, a famous market area where many ethnic non-Han people live, [13.a] (Box 21)
    - August 9-13, 2000 on the streets of Urumqi, [13.b] (Box 21)
    - August 9-13, 2000 Uyghur street musicians of Urumqi, [13.c] (Box 21)
    - August 9-13, 2000 a Uyghur concert with singing and dancing, [13.f-q] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 13-17th 2000 Mageti, Xinjiang Province, [14.a-t and 15.a-f]
      (Bright Sheng was invited to a Uyghur family dinner. During the dinner, five old Mukam players/singers perform the Daolong Mukam almost without stop for six hours. See the Xinjiang part of Bright Sheng's Silk Road Journal)
      - Five old Village peasants performing dolang mukam, [14.a-b] (Box 21)
      - Dancing, [14.c-d, f-h] (Box 21)
        (Dancing is a main feature during the Uyghur's hosted dinner. Usually, the hosts start, and then guests join in)
      - An unusual instrument used by Uyghur musicians, [14.j] (Box 21)
      - Bright Sheng trying to follow dolang mukam's rhythm, [14-q] (Box 21)
      - One of the musicians cooking, [14-t] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 18-19, 2000 in Atush, [15.g-j] (Box 21)
      (inhabited chiefly by the Kilghiz people (another one of the thirteen ethnic groups in Xinjiang). The pictures show the Tan Chang tradition: the singing of Kilghiz folk songs and the playing of one of their representative plucked instruments, the Kumuz. The Kumuz is a two-stringed instrument with a rather small sounding and a narrow neck of about two feet.)
    - ca. August 19-20, 2000 An old musician's house near Ahqi County, a small village in the high rocky mountains, [15.k-t]
      - Left to Right: the best student of the old musician, Mr. Mamaty, Mamaty, and Mrs. Mamaty., [15.l] (Box 21)
      - Bright Sheng with Mr. Mamaty, age 75, [15.n] (Box 21)
        (a very cultured scholar, Mamaty knows much of the Kilghiz culture. Unfortunately, he has not recorded any of his repertoire of songs, which amounts to around 200 pieces. His best student (the one who introduced him to Bright Sheng) knows only roughly half of his songs.)
      - Mr. Mamaty honoring Bright Sheng, [15.r-t] (Box 21)
        (Mr. Mamaty treating Bright Sheng to the highest reception shown for the most honored guests--they kill and cook a whole lamb right in front of the guests and invite them to have it)
      - A young Uyghur cooking, [15.r] (Box 21)
      - Bright Sheng having dinner with Uyghur people, [15.s] (Box 21)
    - August 21-23, 2000 The way to Yining, [16.a-t] (Box 21)
      (The scenery is breathtakingly beautiful. The blue sky blends well with the green and snowy mountain)
    - August 26, 2000 Flame Mountain:, [17.a-h] (Box 21)
      (In legends the Flame Mount was a fire-burning mountain. It is famous scenery on the way to Turpan)
    - circa August 21-26, 2000, The scenery of Xinjiang. Pingyao Ancient City, [17.i-t]and 18.a-h] (Box 21)
    - ca. Ruins of the Great Wall, [18. i-j, n-t] (Box 21)
    - Jiayu gate, part of the Great Wall, [18.h-m] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 21-26, 2000 Bright Sheng on the Silk Road ("Western Territories"), [19.a-i] (Box 21)
    - The scenery of Dong Huang (Cresson Spring and Sand dome), [19.k-q] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 21-29, 2000 The scenery of Xinjiang, [20.a-e] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 26-29, 2000 The scenery on the way to Tian Chi, [20.f-j]
      - Residents living on Tian mountain, [20.j] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 26-29 2000 The scenery of Tian Chi, [20.k-p] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 21-29, 2000 The scenery of Xinjiang, [20.q-r] (Box 21)
    - ca. August 9-29 2000 Uyghur folk song and dance performances, [21.a-t, and 22.a-d]
      - Bright Sheng with Uyghur folk song and dance performers, [22.b-c] (Box 21)
      - Uyghur audience members, [22.d] (Box 21)
    - August 22-23, 2000 Folksong and dance performance at Yining, [22.f-l] (Box 21)
    - August, 2000 Xinjiang, Urumqi, Kazak Singing, [22. p-q] (Box 21)
    - August, 2000 Kilghiz Dinner, [22.r-s] (Box 21)
    - August 26 2000 Turfan, [23.a-r]
      (An old city with a history of at least 2,000 years, Turfan is situated in a vast mountain valley of the Tian Shan Mountains. It had been an important commercial city for the Silk Road. It also is famous for its grapes and for Turfan Mukam.)
      - the old city of Turfan, [23.a-k] (Box 21)
      - Turfan Mukam performing under the grapevines., [23.l-r] (Box 21)
    - August 9-29, 2000 Residents of Xinjiang Province, [24.a-t, and 25.a-q] (Box 21)
    - Instruments, [26.a-t]
      - The Kumzi, [26. a-j] (Box 21)
      - The Tanber, [26. k] (Box 21)
      - The Donbra, [26. l-o] (Box 21)
      - Xun, [26. p] (Box 21)
      - Chinese Cello, [26. q-r] (Box 21)
      - Instruments displayed in the museum, [26. s-t] (Box 21)
    - The city view along the Silk Road of China, [27.a-t]
      - Beijing, [27.c-e] (Box 21)
      - Urumqi, [27.k-m] (Box 21)
    - Along the Silk Road and The Silver River slides (Box 21)
      (7 images of Bright Sheng's opera The Silver River from the Spoleto Festival in 2000 and 43 selected Silk Road slides which were used in the book Along the Silk Road.)
  - Silk Road Writings
    (Articles, interviews, essays, and other information on the Silk Road and Sheng's trip)
- Moving Images
  The Moving Images, 1985-2003 series is comprised of VHS tapes and DVDs of performances of Sheng's works, and interviews with and news segments featuring Sheng.
  - Videotapes
    - Interviews
      - CBS Sunday Morning, November 17, 1985 (Box 22)
        (Bright Sheng and Aaron Copland at Tanglewood in 1985 Recorded at Tanglewood Music Festival; it was the first time Bright Sheng met Leonard Bernstein and Aaron Copland. Soon thereafter, Sheng became Bernstein's composition student for five years)
      - NBC Sunday Today, Interview with Bright Sheng, 1992 (Box 22)
      - UCSD-TV A Conversation with Bright Sheng Summer Fest La Jolla, 1993, 30 min. (Box 22)
        (at)
      - CBS Sunday Morning, Interview with Bright Sheng, June 29, 1997 (Box 22)
      - PBS News Hour, July 3, 1998 (Box 22)
      - Voice of American Chinese Branch, segment on Madame Mao, July 18, 2002, RT: 7:31 (Box 22)
      - Voice of America Chinese Branch, segment on Madame Mao, August 2003, August 2003
      - Asian American, undated (Box 22)
        (Hosted by David Henry Hwang; with guests Bright Sheng; Donna Lkema Chancellor)
      - News Feature with Jim Lehrer segment on Madame Mao, 2003, RT: 10:10 (Box 22)
    - Ceremonial Events
      - Bright Sheng at the White House Dinner honoring Chinese Premier Zhou Rongji April 1999 (Box 22)
    - Performances
      - The Song of Majnun, August 3, 1994 (Box 22)
        (Opera Performance; Librettist: Andrew Porter; Orchestra: Houston Grand Opera; Aspen Opera theater; World Premiere Performance; RT.: 60 min.)
      - The Song of Majnun, March 30, 1996 (Box 22)
        (Opera Performance; Librettist: Andrew Porter; Conductor: Christopher Zimmerman)
      - The Song of Majnun, March 31, 1996 (Box 22)
      - The Silver River, 1997 (Box 22)
        (Librettist: David Henry Hwang; Composer: Bright Sheng)
      - The Silver River, July 28, 1997 (Box 22)
      - The Silver River (1997 Rev. 1999), May 3-13, 2001 (Box 22)
        (Librettist: David Henry Hwang; Composer: Bright Sheng; Singapore; Copyright 2000 by G. Schirmer, Inc.)
      - Chi-Lin, April 2, 2002 (Box 22)
        (Bright Sheng; World Premiere Performance)
  - DVDs
    - Performances
      - The Silver River, 2002 (Box 22)
        (Composer: Bright Sheng; Librettist: David Henry Hwang; Director: Ong Keng Sen; Conductor: Bright Sheng; recorded at Lincoln Center Festival, Lincoln Center, New York City)
        (Copyright 2000 by G. Schirmer, Inc. (ASCAP) NY, NY, July 21, 2000)
      - Madame Mao Act I (Opera in Two Act), July 27, 2003
        (Composer: Bright Sheng; Librettist: Colin Graham; Director: Colin Graham; Conductor: John Fiore; recorded at Santa Fe Opera House, New Mexico, The Santa Fe Opera, 2003 Festival Season. This is the Dress Rehearsal of the World Premiere.)
        - DVD for MAC (Box 22)
        - DVD for PC
Appendix 1
Biographical Essay by Pamela Chen, Bentley Historical Library project archivist and Ph.D. student, Michigan State University, 2004
"I am 100% Chinese. I am also 100% American" is an identity Chinese-American composer Bright Sheng offers of himself. Born on December 6, 1955 in Shanghai, Sheng began to study piano with his mother at age four. During China's Cultural Revolution, he was sent to the remote province of Qinghai, where for seven years he performed as a pianist and percussionist in a folk music and dance troupe. He also collected and studied folk music during his years in Qinghai. When China's universities reopened in 1978, he was among the first students with the best grades who were admitted to the Shanghai Conservatory of Music. He earned his undergraduate degree in music composition there. He moved to New York City in 1982, and received graduate degrees there at Queens College (M.A.) and Columbia University (D.M.A.). Among his important teachers were Leonard Bernstein (composition and conducting), George Perle, Hugo Weisgall, Chou Wen-Chung, and Jack Beeson.
"Give me five years. If I do not succeed as a musician, I will choose another profession." Bright Sheng made this promise to his father the year after his arrival in the United States, at a time when his father was pushing him to change his mind from music to business. His father had warned him that, "music will never make you a good living." Bright Sheng's talent, however, emerged of its own accord soon after he had given his word to his father. In addition to the awards he received in China and Europe, Sheng also received a number of prizes in the United States already as a student: from the National Endowment for the Arts; American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters; the Guggenheim, Rockefeller, Naumberg, Jerome, Koussevitzky, and Copland foundations; the Mary Flagler Cary Charitable Trust; the Kennedy Center; and Tanglewood Music Center.
In 2001, Sheng was the recipient of the Michigan Arts Award and a Rackham fellowship from the University of Michigan. He has been a member of the composition faculty at the University of Michigan since 1995, and now holds the title of Leonard Bernstein Distinguished University Professor of Music. In April 1999, at the invitation of President William Clinton, Sheng received a special commission from the White House to create a new work for a state dinner. The resulting Three Songs for Pipa and Cello was premiered by soloists Wu Man and Yo Yo Ma during a dinner hosted by the president at which the Chinese Premiere, Zhou Rongji, was honored. Of all of Sheng's awards, the most significant is the so-called "Genius Award" -- the MacArthur Foundation Fellowship. Awarded in November 2001 with a cash prize of $500,000, Sheng was proclaimed by the Foundation Committee to be "an innovative composer who merges diverse musical customs in works that transcend conventional aesthetic boundaries." His music was further described as "a fresh voice in cross-cultural music." The foundation committee anticipated that "Bright Sheng will continue to be an important leader in exploring and bridging musical traditions."
Inspired by the folk music of China, Bright Sheng's music is noted for its lyrical, limpid melodies, particularly from Qinghai; a Shostakovich sense of breath in the music phrases; a Bartokian sense of rhythmic propulsion; and musical and theatrical gestures borrowed or derived from Chinese opera. Sheng's works are also well known for their dramatic style and historical signification. Two of his major orchestral works were indeed inspired by events in recent Chinese history. They are H'un: In Memoriam 1966-76 and Naking! Nanking!, a work for pipa and orchestra honoring those who endured the atrocities of the Rape of Nanjing.
Within the first week of the new century, Bright Sheng had two world premieres. One was Naking! Nanking commissioned and premiered on January 2, 2000 by the North German Radio Symphony Orchestra in Hamburg, and conducted by Christoph Eschenbach. The other was Red Silk Dance, a piano concerto premiered on January 6, 2000 by the commissioning Boston Symphony Orchestra in Hamburg, with the soloist Emanuel Ax and conductor Robert Spano. Around the same time, there were major performances of Sheng's instrumental music. These included the world premiere of Tibetan Dance (2001) by the Verdehr Trio; the New York premieres of Red Silk Dance (Ax, Masur, New York Philharmonic); Naking! Naking! (Spano, Brooklyn Philharmonic); Flute Moon (Schwarz, New York Chamber Symphony); China Dreams (Spano, Saint Louis Symphony); and Leonard Slakin's presentation of H'un with the National Symphony in Washington, D.C. H'un had been commissioned and premiered in 1988 by the New York Chamber Symphony. This frequently performed piece, of "naked emotionalism ...a battle of the spirit" according to The New York Times, is Sheng's landmark portrait of the Chinese Cultural Revolution. It established his reputation as a composer and has been performed by major orchestras around the world, including the New York Philharmonic, Chicago Symphony, Cleveland Orchestra, and Tokyo Philharmonic. Kurt Masur and the New York Philharmonic performed H'un in six cities on their 1993 European tour; in 1994, it was also featured at the Warsaw Autumn Festival.
In 2002, Spano led the world premiere performance, with the Brooklyn Philharmonic, of Sheng's spirited Tibetan Swing, a ten-minute concert opener based upon a Tibetan dance rhythm and co-commissioned by the Singapore Symphony; the Dortmund Philharmonic performed Naking! Naking! under the direction of Arthur Fagen, the city's general music director; Hugh Wolf conducted Postcards with Frankfurt's Radio-Symfonie-Orchester; and the Dusseldof Symphony, conducted by John Fiore, gave the European premiere of Tibetan Swing. The Liverpool Philharmonic, under the guidance of its music director Gerard Schwarz, one of the composer's first champions in the West, offered concerts of Sheng's chamber music as well as performances of H'un. In March 2003, Carnegie Hall presented a Sheng Portrait concert in their "Making Music" series with members of the New York Philharmonic; and the New York Philharmonic, featuring soloists Yo-Yo Ma and Emanuel Ax conducted by David Zinman, premiered a major commission by Sheng: a quadruple concerto for cello, piano, pipa, and sheng entitled the Silk Road Region in the Summer of 2000.
In early February 2004, Bright Sheng enjoyed another world premiere, as Gerard Schewarz led soprano Jane Eaglen and the Seattle Symphony in the first performance of the orchestral song-cycle The Phoenix. Based on Hans Christian Andersen's mythical bird with Sheng's own English lyric adaptation, The Phoenix was co-commissioned by the Danish Radio Orchestra for the coinciding occasions of the Seattle Symphony's centennial celebration and for the bicentennial birthday of Andersen. In April 2004, the Seattle Symphony and Eaglen brought the work to Carnegie Hall for its New York premiere. Other firsts of Sheng around this time include the ISCM World Music Days 2003 presenting the Slovenian premiere of his Concertino for Clarinet and String Quartet by soloist Mate Bekavac and the Tartini String Quartet; Orchestra Luxembourg's national premiere of Flute Moon; the world premiere of his new choral work for young voice, The Boatmen's Song, performed by the Young People's Chorus of New York City in April 2004; and the Asian premiere of his quadruple concerto The Song and Dance of Tears by The Silk Road Ensemble (featuring Yo-Yo Ma) and the Singapore Symphony in June 2004.
Bright Sheng's compositional gifts have also shown him to be a natural for the theater. In July 2003, the Santa Fe Opera presented the world premiere of Madam Mao. This two-act opera portrays Jiang Qing, Chairman Mao's repressed, vengeful wife who was one of the leading architects of the disastrous Cultural Revolution that nearly destroyed China. Set to a libretto by its stage director Colin Graham, the work garnered worldwide acclaim. Heidi Waleson of The Wall Street Journal wrote that, "The opera begins and ends with the body of Jiang, who hanged herself in prison, dangling from the roof; in between, Mr. Sheng offers us an artist's insight and understanding of that startling image. She adds that, "Stylistically, Sheng is a master of fusion." Deborah Baker from The Daily Camera.com wrote that, "Sheng's writing for the voice is quite beguiling, with ruminative duets with wistful melodies, cushioned by subdued orchestral music that finds common ground between wide-space Coplandesque harmony and the pentatonic elements of Chinese idioms. The orchestra writing is brilliant." Said Anthony Tommasini, The New Yotk Times, "Sheng's [style] is an exquisite blend of the musical East and West." Mark Swed, Los Angeles Times, observed that, "Every aspect of this production was magnificent. No scene is too long, and there is plenty of contrast between violence and warm lyricism. Sheng's music is eclectic and the scoring is imaginative." Michael Kennedy, the Telegraph (London), called it "...extraordinary music and a riveting evening in the theater."
Sheng's important works for the theater have extended to dance. In 2002, choreographer Helgi Tomasson compiled for the San Francisco Ballet three of Sheng's extant pieces as a new work entitled Chi-Lin. (The title refers to the unicorn, one of the four mythical beasts in Chinese mythology). Sheng conducted the premiere of Chi-Lin, as well as the company's tour performances in New York City. Chi-Lin was also presented at the Kennedy Center in Washington, D.C. by the troupe. At the North Carolina Dance Theater, Jean-Pierre Bonnefoux choreographed Sheng's Four Movements for Piano Trio as the work Zoomin'.
In the summer of 2000, the Spoleto USA Festival unveiled one of Bright Sheng's most important recent works: a multi-cultural music theater piece entitled The Silver River (1997; rev. 2000). Based on an ancient Chinese tale about star-crossed lovers, and set to a libretto by David Henry Hwang, this visually stunning production was directed by Ong Keng Sen, the Singaporean director well-known for a creative fusion of diverse Asian theatrical genres. The Silver River has been performed subsequently in Philadelphia at the Prince Music Theatre Festival; in Singapore; and in July 2002 it was a highlight of the Lincoln Center Festival in New York, where it was accompanied by concerts of, and symposia on, Sheng's music.
While serving as composer-in-residence for the Lyric Opera of Chicago from 1989 to 1992, Sheng wrote The Song of Majnun (1992) -- a one act "Persian Romeo and Juliet" -- in collaboration with librettist Andrew Porter. Majnun has subsequently received five other productions nationwide and was recorded by the Houston Grand Opera on the Delos label. Sheng's musical passion will also soon materialize as a Broadway show. He is currently working on a Broadway show to be based on one of China's four famous stories, The West Journey.
Bright Sheng has collaborated with many distinguished musicians including Leonard Bernstein, Kurt Masur, Christoph Eschenbach, Gerard Schwarz, Leonard Slatkin, David Zinman, Neemi Jarvi, Robert Spano, Hugh Wolff, Yo-Yo Ma, Peter Serkin, Emanuel Ax, and Cho-Liang Lin. In addition to the ensembles mentioned above, many other organizations have commissioned and performed his works including the Boston Symphony, Philadelphia Orchestra, the Los Angeles Philharmonic, Houston Symphony, Seattle Symphony, Saint Paul Chamber Orchestra, Carnegie Hall, the CBC Radio Orchestra, Winnipeg Symphony, Orchestra Luxembourg, the Shanghai Symphony, Singapore Symphony, the Danish and Finnish Radio Symphony Orchestras, Hong Kong Philharmonic, Orchestre de Paris, Orchestra Sinfonica dell'Accademia Nazionale de Santa Cecilia, Italy, the BBC Symphony Orchestra, Rotterdam's Philarmonisch Orkest, Frankfurt Radio Symphony, Royal Liverpool Philharmonic Orchestra, National Symphony of Russia, National Symphony of Spain, the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, the Tanglewood and Aspen music festivals, the Cheltenham (U.K.) International Music Festival, and the Hong Kong Arts Festival.
In addition to composing, Sheng enjoys an active career as a conductor, concert pianist, university scholar, and frequent music advisor and artistic director to leading orchestras and festivals. He has performed in many of the world's most important music venues, including Lincoln Center, Carnegie Hall, and the Kennedy Center. He has been a guest conductor and pianist with the San Francisco Symphony, New York Chamber Symphony, Seattle Symphony Orchestra, Royal Liverpool Philharmonic Orchestra, Vancouver Symphony Orchestra, Hong Kong Chinese Orchestra, China National Symphony Orchestra, New West Symphony Orchestra, Lexington Symphony Orchestra, Orchestra 2001 (Philadelphia), Asian Youth Orchestra, San Francisco Ballet, Lincoln Center Festival, Tanglewood Music Center, Prince Music Theater (Philadelphia), Spoleto Festival, Brevard Music Festival, Silk Road Project Workshop (Tanglewood Music Center), Bravo! Vail Valley Music Festival Bowdoin Summer Music Festival, Santa Fe Chamber Music Festival, Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, La Jolla Chamber Music Festival, Seattle International Music Festival, Seattle Chamber Music Festival, and University of Michigan Contemporary Direction.